[Music]
Reedman reads
the Giver by Lois Lowry, narrated by Fraser Reedman.
Chapter 18.
[Music]
Give her Jonas asked the next afternoon,.
"Do you ever think about release?"? "Do you mean my own release, or just the general
topic of release?"? "Both,, I guess.. I apologize. I mean, I should have been
more precise., But I don't know exactly what I meant.". "Sit back up.. No need to
lie down while we're talking.". Jonas,, who had already been stretched out on the
bed when the question came to his mind,, sat back up.. "I guess I do think about it
occasionally,", The Giver said.. "I think about my own release when I'm in an
awful lot of pain.. I wish I could put in a request for it, sometimes.,
But I'm not permitted to do that until the new Receiver is trained.".
"Me,", Jonas said in a dejected voice.. He was not looking forward to the end of
the training, when he would become the new Receiver.. It was clear to him what a
terribly difficult and lonely life it was, despite the owner. I can't request
release either,", Jonas pointed out.. "It was in my rules.". The Giver laughed
harshly.. "I know that. They hammered out those rules after the failure 10 years
ago.". Jonas had heard again and again now the reference to the previous failure.,
But he still did not know what had happened 10 years before.. "Giver,", he
said,, ""tell me what happened., Please."."
The Giver shrugged.. "On the surface,, it was quite simple.. A receiver to be was
selected, the way you were.. The selection went smoothly enough.. The Ceremony was
held, and the selection was made.. The crowd cheered, as they did for you.. The
new Receiver was puzzled and a little frightened, as you were.". "My parents told
me it was a female.". The Giver nodded..
Jonas thought of his favorite female,, Fiona,, and shivered.. He wouldn't want
his gentle friend to suffer the way he had,, taking on the memories.. "What was
she like?"? he asked The Giver.. The Giver looked sad, thinking about it.. "She was a
remarkable young woman., Very self-possessed and serene., Intelligent,, eager to learn.".
He shook his head and drew a deep breath..
""You know, Jonas,, when she came to me in this room,, when she presented herself to
begin her trading," Jonas interrupted and with a question., ""Can you tell me
her name?? My parents said it wasn't to be spoken again in the community., But
couldn't you just say it to me?"?
The Giver hesitated painfully,, as if saying the name aloud might be excruciating..
"Her name was Rosemary,", he told Jonas, finally..
""Rosemary.? I like that name."," The Giver went on.. "When she came to me for the
first time,, she sat there in the chair where you sat on your first day..
She was eager and excited and a little scared..
We talked.. I tried to explain things as well as I could." ""The way you did to me."?"
The Giver chuckled rofully. "The explanations are difficult.. The whole
thing is so beyond one's experience., But I tried.." And she listened carefully..
Her eyes were very luminous,, I remember.".
He looked up suddenly..
"Jonas,, I gave you a memory that I told you was my favorite.. I still have a
shred of it left. The room, with the family, and the grandparents?".
Jonas nodded.. Of course, he remembered..
"Yes,", he said.. "It had that wonderful feeling in it.. You told me it was love.".
"You understand, then, that that's what I felt for Rosemary,". The Giver explained..
"I loved her..
"I feel it for you, too,"," he added.. ""What happened to her?"?" Jonas asked.. "Her
training began.. She received well,, as you do.. She was so enthusiastic., So
delighted to experience new things.. I remember her laughter...". His voice
faltered and trailed off.. ""What happened?"?" Jonas asked again, after a
moment.. ""Please tell me."," The Giver closed his eyes.. ""It broke my heart,,
Jonas,. to transfer pain to her., But it
was my job.. It was what I had to do, the
way I've had to do it to you."." The room was silent.. Jonas waited.. Finally, The
Giver continued.. "Five weeks.. That was all.. I gave her happy memories:. a ride
on the merrygoround, a kitten to play with;, a picnic.. Sometimes I chose one
just because I knew it would make her laugh,. and I so treasured the sound of
that laughter in this room that had always been so silent.. "But she was like
you,, Jonas.. She wanted to experience everything.. She knew that it was her responsibility..
And so she asked me for more difficult memories.". Jonas held his breath for a
moment.. "You didn't give her war,, did you?? Not after just 5 weeks?".
The Giver shook his head inside. No.. And I didn't give her physical pain., But I
gave her loneliness.
I gave her loss.. I transferred a memory of a child taken from its parents.. That
was the first one.. She appeared stunned at its end. Jonah swallowed.. Rosemary,
and her laughter, had begun to seem real to him,, and he pictured her looking up
from the bed of memories,, shocked., The Giver continued.. "I backed off,, gave her
more little delights.. But everything changed, once she knew about pain.. I
could see it in her eyes.". "She wasn't brave enough. Jonah suggested.. The Giver
didn't respond to the question.. "She insisted that I continue,, that I not
spare her.. She said it was her duty., And I knew,, of course,, that she was correct..
"I couldn't bring myself to inflict physical pain on her., But I gave her
anguish of many kinds., Poverty,, and hunger, and terror..
"I had to,, Jonas..
It was my job., And she had been chosen.".
The Giver looked at him imploringly..
Jonas stroked his hand.. "Finally, one afternoon,, we finished for the day..
It had been a hard session.. I tried to finish—, —as I do with you—, —by
transferring something happy and cheerful., But the times of laughter were
gone by then.. She stood up very silently,, frowning, as if she were making
a decision. And she came over to me and put her arms around me.. She kissed my
cheek.". As Jonas watched,, The Giver stroked his own cheek,, recalling the
touch of Rosemary's lips 10 years before.. "She left here that day,, left
this room,, and did not go back to her dwelling..
I was notified by the Speaker that she had gone directly to the Chief Elder and
asked to be released.".
"But it's against the rules!. The receiver in training can't apply for release.
It's in your rules,, Jonas.. But it wasn't in hers.. She asked for release,, and they
had to give it to her.. I never saw her again.". So that was the failure,, Jonas
thought. was obvious that it saddened to give her very deeply.. But it didn't seem
such a terrible thing, after all.. And he, Jonas, would never have done it—, —never
requested release,, no matter how difficult his training became.. The Giver
needed a successor, and he had been chosen.. A thought occurred to Jonas..
Rosemary had been released very early in her training.. What if something happened
to him,, Jonas?? He had a whole year's worth of memories now. Give her, he
asked,. "I can't request release,. I know that.. But what if something happened:, an
accident?? What if I fell into the river like the little Four, Caleb, did?? Well,,
that doesn't make sense because I'm a good swimmer.. But what if I couldn't
swim, and fell into the river and was lost?? Then there wouldn't be a new
Receiver,. but you would already have given away an awful lot of important
memories,. so even though they would select a new Receiver,, the memories
would be gone except for the shreds that you have left of them?. And then what if—"?
He started to laugh, suddenly..
"I sound like my sister, Lily,", he said, amused at himself.. The Giver looked at
him gravely.. ""You just stay away from the river,, my friend,"." he said., ""The
community lost Rosemary after 5 weeks, and it was a disaster for them.. I don't
know what the community would do if they lost you."."
"Why was it a disaster?"? "I think I mentioned to you once,", The Giver
reminded him, "when she was gone,, the memories came back to the people..
If you were to be lost in the river, Jonas,, your memories would not be lost
with you.. Memories are forever..
"Rosemary had only those five weeks worth,, and most of them were good ones..
But there were those few terrible memories,, the ones that had overwhelmed her..
For a while, they overwhelmed the community.. All those feelings!. They'd
never experienced that before.. "I was so devastated by my own grief at her loss,
and my own feeling of failure, that I didn't even try to help them through it..
I was angry,, too.".
The Giver was quiet for a moment,, obviously thinking.. "You know,", he said,
finally,, ""if they lost you, with all the training you've had now,, they'd have all
those memories again themselves."."
Jonas made a face.. "They'd hate that.".
"They certainly would..
They wouldn't know how to deal with it all.". "The only way I deal with it is by
having you there to help me,". Jonas pointed out with a sigh.. The Giver nodded.. "I suppose,",
he said slowly,. "that I could—". "You could what?"?
The Giver was still deep in thought..
After a moment,, he said,, ""If you floated off in the river,, I suppose I could help
the whole community the way I've helped you..
It's an interesting concept.. I need to think about it some more.. Maybe we'll
talk about it again sometime., But not now..
"I'm glad you're a good swimmer,, Jonas.
stay away from the river.". He laughed a little,, but the laughter was not light-hearted.
His thoughts seemed to be elsewhere,, and his eyes were very troubled.
[Music]